<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>I pray you be not angry, for I will make you merry a pleasant and merry dialogue, betweene two trauellers, as they met on the high-way</title>
            <author>Breton, Nicholas, 1545?-1626?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116183</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851400</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851400</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16671</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16754)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16671)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1371:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>I pray you be not angry, for I will make you merry a pleasant and merry dialogue, betweene two trauellers, as they met on the high-way</title>
                  <author>Breton, Nicholas, 1545?-1626?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. M[athewes] for Samuel Rand and are to be sold at his shop at Holborne Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Nicholas Breton.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Another edition of STC 3661, omitting the preface.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: I pray you be not angry for I will make you merry.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16671:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16671:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I Pray you be not Angry, for I will make you merry</p>
            <p>A pleaſant and merry dialogue, betweene two Trauellers, as they met on the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Samuel Rand</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at Holborne Bridge. 1624.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:16671:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16671:2"/>
            <head>A merrie Dialogue betweene two Trauellers vpon the High-way, touching their <hi>Croſſes:</hi> and of the vertue of <hi>patience.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Fabiano, <hi>and</hi> Fernuno.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fernuno.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Abian,</hi> Good morrow: how do you? and how farre walke you this way?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fabian.</speaker>
               <p>I do as you ſée, neither of the beſt, nor the worſt: and am trauelling not very farre; &amp; yet ſomewhat more then a pretty walke; about ſome hundreth miles or two for a breathing, to teach the dauncing legges of my youth, to plodde for the prouiſion of mine old age: and ſince it is no better, it is well it is no worſe: For ſince I haue done my ſelfe more wrong, then I can make my ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends, I muſt content my ſelfe with a pudding, while other may feaſt, that haue better fare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fern.</speaker>
               <p>Then, <hi>I pray you be not Angrie:</hi> for <hi>Patience</hi> is a playſter for all paine, it is the very poyſon of all ſorrow, a preparatiue to all comfort, and the onely quieter of a troubled ſpirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
               <p>Why how now? Haue youe béene a Scholler ſince I ſaw you: Truely I deſire not to trouble your memory, with ſaying ouer your leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon without booke: all your Aduerbes and your Prouerbes, will not doe me a pinnes worth of pleaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fern.</speaker>
               <p>Oh <hi>Fabian!</hi> haue patience <hi>be not angrie</hi> with your Fortune, there are Flouds as well as Ebbes: <hi>Time</hi> hath his turne and <hi>Fortune</hi> may be as great a friend, as ſhée hath béene an enemie: the Starres may one day ſhine as well ouer your houſe, as your neighbours; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtay your houre, you know not when it will come; and therefore take no thought: <hi>I pray you be not Angrie.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:16671:3"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
               <p>Well <hi>Fernuno,</hi> to your ſentences: let mée tell you, that you know that I know, that you know, that when you and I did firſt know one another, you knew the world was better with mée, then to let mée plodde vp and downe in this manner, with no more company but my Dogge, and my plaine Cudgell: but tis no matter, all is one; for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing plaide wily beguily with my ſelfe, I can thanke no body for my hard bargaine: for in the time of my youth (the moſt perilous point of mans age) falling into ſuch acquaintance as were ſmally to my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, as well of the Maſculine as the Femenine gender, who ſo long fed my humour with follie, that I fell almoſt into a Conſumption, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſound the nature of the diſeaſe: at length, (though ſomewhat late, yet better late, then neuer) remembring that my father leſt me more Land then Wit; and Nature being more Miſtris then Reaſon ouer my ill ruled Senſes: and ſéeing the world at ſuch a paſſe, that I could haue well wiſhed to haue béene out of it: finding my Friends ſcorne of mée, my Foes feoffe at mée, ſome few pitty mée, and few com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort mée, I reſolued to ſhake of my Shake-ragges, and to retire my ſelfe vnto ſome ſolitary place; where, hauing left one. Foole, to laugh at another; one villane to cut anothers throate, and one Honeſt man to be example to a whole Pariſh, I betooke mée to a trauelling life, rather to heare then to ſpeake how the World went: and to note the courſes of the Wiſe, rather then to enter into the courſes of the Wicked: whereof the World is ſo full, that a man can ſcarce eſcape their infection: Why? if I ſhould tell you how I haue brae vſed among them, you would ſay I had good cauſe <hi>to be Angry</hi> with my ſelfe, or ſome body elſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fern.</speaker>
               <p>And yet I ſay, <hi>I pray you be not Angry:</hi> For, if it be with your ſelfe, Fretting will but bréed Melancholy; and Melancholy bring you to ſuch a Sickneſſe, that you may repent it when it is too late. And <hi>to bee Angry</hi> with any other, if you cannot reuenge it, it is a folly: if you doe it is vncharitable; for you muſt forgiue. For, if I ſhould tell you of ſome tricks that were put vpon mee, when I was as wiſe as a Gooſe on Beadlame Gréene, I ſhould make you beléeue that, although I prea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h <hi>Patience</hi> to you, I ſhould haue cauſe to haue little acqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntance with her my ſelfe: But ſpight of the Deuill, I hope to goe to heauen: and though I carry more Croſſes in my heart then in my Purſe, yet I hope (with my fellow Begger) to be in <hi>Abr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hams</hi> booſome, when a rich Churle ſhall dance with <hi>Diues</hi> in a worſe place: and therefore as a friend, let me ſay to you, knowing what is good for you; Whatſoeuer Fortune be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall you, <hi>I pray you be not Angry.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:16671:3"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt confeſſe it is good Councell to haue <hi>Patience;</hi> for <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> is a preety Vertue, but that it waits vpon a number of Villaines: But let mée tell you, if a man ſpend all the money in his purſo vpon a company of vnthankfull Villaines, and when hée commeth to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of his Purſe, and there finding nothing. Intreateth with his friends (as he hath held them) but for an Ordinary or two; and ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingly put off, cannot get a Penny among them: What can you haue in all the rule of <hi>Patience?</hi> onely fret at the heart to heare men ſay, <hi>I pray you be not Angry.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fern.</speaker>
               <p>And yet let me tell you, That when <hi>Anger</hi> will not auaile him, it is better to be <hi>Patient,</hi> then <hi>Angry:</hi> for I haue heard it ſpoken by a Wiſe man. <hi>That he who cannot bee Angry, is a Foole: but hee that will bee Angry, is more Foole:</hi> For when I was (as you ſaid, and I may ſay) in the prime of my time, I may ſay in the fooliſh pride of youth, when all the Gold in the Pariſh, was Copper to my Siluer: and my Wit was beyond Reaſon; when I was the onely Foole of the World: Oh then (to tell you) I was ouer taken in the halfe turne, would make one runne out of his wittes, and into them againe if it were poſſible: for ſay this, If a man haue no deformity in his proportion, is no Wood-cock for his ordinary courſe of Witte, hath Wealth enough to liue by his Neighbours without borrowing, is of Parentage with the beſt of the Pariſh, is in the way of good ſpéede with a Match worth the making of: and leauing all honeſt wiſe, and good councell, forſaketh his Fortune, and binds himſelfe prentice during life to an ill fauoured Baggage, the worſt Child that her father had, whoſe beauty is like the backe of a ſea-coale Chimney; and for proportion, the true proportion of a ſea-crab, as much wit as a gray Gooſe, and manners as a blind Mare, and no more wealth then the Wooll on a ſhorne Shéepe: beſides, the iſſue of idle drunkenneſſe, which being grounded in all foolliſhneſſe, can away with nothing but worſe then nothing: whoſe tongue can kéepe no ſecrets, whoſe heart can thinke no goodneſſe, and whoſe life is a world of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietueſſe: and ſpight of his heart hauing taken hee for better or worſe, (when ſhée cannot well be worſe, and will be no better) muſt hold out his life worſe then ten deaths with her: Say your ſelfe, that when a man thinkes of this miſery, it would fret him to the very heart: But where is the remedy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
               <p>Oh! <hi>I pray you be not angry:</hi> For if a man ſhould haue a Siſter whome hée Loueth Deacely, whoſe Beauty with Vertue, were a Dowry for a Prince, her Linage Noble, her Perſonage comly, her
<pb facs="tcp:16671:4"/>nature kind, and her gouernment ſo diſcréet, that by the iudgement of the wife, we was a match for the worthy: to ſée this bleſſed creature, by the crueltie of the Fates beſtowed vpon the baſtard ſonne of a Begger, whoſe Father was a billaine, his Mother a ſoole, and he a Changeling: whoſe eyes were thrée foote out of his head, his noſe too long for his month, and his skinne to wide for his face, his heade like a high-way with a little heath on either ſide, and his beard bending to the Ale-houſe, from thence came the originall of his little honor: and for his vnder pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, an anſwering to the upper parts: whoſe wit was onely practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in villanie, whoſe hart ſtudied but Hell, while his ſoule was ſworn ſeruant to the Deuill: and yet this raſcall Viper ſhall, onely with his golden I lawes, créepe into the hands (for in the heart hée could neuer) of a pretty Wench, and carry her a way into ſuch a world of diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that ſhée could neuer leaue ſorrowing till ſhée had got into her graue. Would it not fret ſuch a Brother as had ſuch a Siſter; or chafe ſuch a Louer as had ſuch a Loue, to ſée ſuch an ouerthrow of his comfort, or confuſion of his kind hope.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fern.</speaker>
               <p>Oh! <hi>I Pray you be not Angrie:</hi> For Marriage and Hanging (ſome ſay) goe by deſtinte: and although Hanging is but a ſhort paine, and marriage is a lingring miſery, where diſagreement is a deadly life: yet ſince wee cannot goe againſt the will of the higher powers, <hi>Patience</hi> is a playſter, that will in time drawe a mans heart out of his belly, except hée haue more wit to gouerne his paſſion. But leauing loue toyes, let me tell you, that if a man finding by ſome old writings in his mothers cheſt, that his Father had Title to a peece of Land, which for want of a good purſe, he durſt neuer make challenge to it, and ſay that I were the man, and I by the witneſſe of my honeſt ancient neighbours, can approue it in good conſcience to be mine owne in right of Law; and thereupon aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king counſell, and paying for words by waight, and by my learned coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell perſwaded that it is mine paſt all plea. And thus playing with my Noſe, or rather with my purſe, till all be ſpent; with <hi>Demurrs</hi> &amp; tricks he drines me to beggery, with ſuing for mine owne right, while he goes gay with my money, and I ſtarne with his words; a vengance vpon his craftie conueyance. Would not this fret a mans ſoule to thinke on it, and cannot helpe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
               <p>Now God forbid; <hi>I pray you be not Angry;</hi> for Law was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalued for the beſt; and though in all profeſſions ſome are too blame, yet no doubt, but ſome haue ſuch conſciences, that they would not be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a kingdome; but Courts muſt haue their fees, and Schollers muſt
<pb facs="tcp:16671:4"/>not ſtudy for nothing. But for that I am no good Lawyer, nor euer met with any bribes, I haue nothing to ſay to them; but wiſh the wicked their reward, while the honeſt may take héede by their example: &amp; ſo lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them all to the day of their death, I will tell you of another matter.</p>
               <p>Say that I had a friend, at leaſt as I take him &amp; louing him ſo dearely that I durſt, nay I doe truſt him with all that I am worth; and being to take a voyage either vpon command or commodity, fearing ſome ill courſes to be taken for my children if I ſhould die, knowing women ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſo ſorrowfull for a loſt husband, that they will not tarry long for a new; and what fathers in law be to orphants, while widdowes ſigh &amp; ſay nothing, hauing (in truſt to my friend) made a ſecret déed of gift of all my eſtate vnto him, the rather that my wife and children may fare the better; and now I haue eſcaped many dangers by ſea and land, and ſpoyled of all that I had with me, come home, hoping to finde comfort yet at my owne houſe with that I left behinde me; and there no ſooner en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in at the gate, but with a coy looke, and a cold welcome, I find my wife either turned out of doores, or ſo badly vſed within, that ſhe could well wiſh to be without; &amp; then, if I take it vnkindly, be bidden mend it as I can; and ſo with a frowne or a frumpe, almoſt thruſt out of doores, be conſtrained to goe to Law for mine owne liuing, while my miſtaken friend hauing turned Turke, cares for nothing but his owne commodity, &amp; contrary to all conſcience, playes with me for my owne money, till the Lawyer and he together, haue wonne me quite out of mine owne land and ſo play me the Traytor with my truſt; leaue me in the miſery of my fortune, to end my vnhappy dayes; Now can you ſay to this, <hi>I pray you be not Angry?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fern.</speaker>
               <p>Yes very well; for ſince you ſee no remedy, but God is ſuch a God in the world, as makes the deuil work many wonders among men, is it not better with <hi>patience</hi> to indure a croſſe, thou to crucifie the ſoule with impatience. But ſay that you ſhould haue a wife that you thought did loue you well, when ſhee would ſtroke your beard, and neuer lie from your lippes, and would ſpeake you as faire as <hi>Eue</hi> did <hi>Adam,</hi> when ſhée couſned him with an Apple; would not abide an Oath for a buſhell of Gold, and be ſo ſparing of her purſe, that ſhée would not looſe the dropping of her noſe: bridle it in her countenance like a Mare that were knapping on a Cow-thiſtle: would weare no ruffes but of the ſmal ſet, though of the ſluect Lawne that might be gotten, and edged with a Lace of the beſt faſhion: would not abide no imbrodery in her apparell, yet haue the beſt ſtuffe ſhée could lay her hands on; and feede ſparingly
<pb facs="tcp:16671:5"/>at dinner, when ſhée had broke her faſt in the bed; and miſſed not a Sermon, though ſhée profited little by the word; This diſſembling péece of fleſh, making a ſhew of lamentation, cut of the aboundance of her little loue, for lacko of your good company, if you were but a mile out of the Towne: &amp; if you were to take a iourney, would lay an Onion to her eies, to draw out the Rhewme inſtéed of teares: &amp; hauing eaten an apple, with pinching in a backward wind, ſend out a belching, ſigh for ſorrow of the abſence of her Gooſe-man: and then after all theſe, and a world of other tricks, to bring a man in a bad beléefe of her good minde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning home a night ſooner then expected, &amp; a yéere ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ner then welcome, ſhould (hauing Keyes to your owne Doores) come in, and finde in your owne bed botwixt the armes (I goe no lower) of your too much beloued the liuing carkaſſe of a lubberly raſcall, or perhaps the perfumed corpes of ſome dainty compation, working vpon the ground of your pleaſure to plant the fruite of idle fancy, to the horne-griefe of your poore heart; could you be pacified with, <hi>I pray you be not Angry.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
               <p>Indéede you put mée to it, with an, If: But I hope there are no ſuch women; fie for ſhame, it were enough to make murder: but <hi>Patience</hi> being the meane to ſaue many a mans life, &amp; that perhaps being the firſt fault, and ſhée vpon repentance after a ſecret reprehenſion likely to turne honeſt, were it not better to ſteale away, and haue her maid to wake her, the matter cleanly ſhuffled vp, and ſhée with ſorrow rather to confeſſe it in ſecret, and to be ſorry for it, and in ſhame of her fault to leaue it, while few know it; rather then in a fury or franzy bring in your neighbours, raiſe vp your houſe, beate your wife, impriſon the knaue, bring your wife to ſhame, and make the world priuie to your cuckoldry: and ſo ſhée in a deſperate madneſſe, either ſhameleſſe after a little ſhame, or graceleſſe in impatience to beare her correction, either cut her owne throate, or yours, or both; and ſo all come to conſenſion, through lacke of a little charitable diſcretion: No, God forbid, for rather then any ſuch miſchance ſhould fall, is it not better to ſay, <hi>I pray you be not Angrie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For to quit your diſcontentment, ſay that I ſhould (as God forbid I ſhould) haue married an honeſt woman, that hath brought mée many pretty Children, is a good huſwife in her houſe, carefull for her children, and louing both to them and me; and for the ſpace of many yeares, with a good opinion of all her neighbours, and good credit with all that know her, had paſſed ſome ſcore of yeares or two with mée, with as much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment as a reaſonable man might deſire: &amp; to make her amends for all her kindneſſe, I ſhould either take a whore into my houſe, or kéepe her
<pb facs="tcp:16671:5"/>as a hackney at, racke &amp; manger abroad ſo long, till being led by the noſe to beleeue that ſhe loues me, when I pay for the nurſing of halfe a doſen of baſtards: of which, if I be the wicked Father, my conſcience hath little comfort in: and if any other (as it is moſt likely) be the father or fathers, how am I beguiled to play poore noddy, to let my purſe bloud, to pay for the maintaining of anothers pleaſure? And at the laſt, if ſhe find me abridge my lyberality, in a venemous humor come with an outery to my doore, with a neſt of her fellow beggers, and there with rayling vpon me, calling mée old leather, whoremonger, and I know not what; lay her brats downe before my gate, &amp; ſo with a gapeing mouth goeth her way leauing mée to my purſe onely, to ſéeke the ſauing of my credit, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a griefe vnto my wife, a ſorrow to my Children, and a laughing ſtocke to mine enemies, a by-word among my neighbours, a ſhame to my ſelfe, and an enemie to mine owne ſoule: and thus ſéeing my wealth waſted, my credit loſt or impaired, and God ſo diſpleaſed, that I know not which way to turne my ſelfe; Shall I neither <hi>be Angrie</hi> with the whoore for bewraying me, nor with my ſelfe to let her ſo befoole me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fern.</speaker>
               <p>No, I ſay as I did, <hi>I pray you be not Angry;</hi> for ſhee did but her kinde, to vſe her eyes to the benefit of the reſt of her members: and therefore you being a man of iudgement, ought rather to be ſorry for her wickedneſſe, then to ſhew your owne weakeneſſe, in ſuch yeares to haue a thought of wantonneſſe: but ſure the fleſh is weake, and the ſtrongeſt may fall better is a ſorrowfull repentance, then a fretting madneſſe: and ſince fretting at your owne folly, to ſell all the land you haue, wil not get you a foote of earth more then your graue, bee not at warres with your ſelfe to no purpoſe: ceaſe from doing euill, make much of your honeſt wife, ſerue God in true repentance, and the Diuell ſhall doe you no hurt: for, is it not better to beare your croſſe: eſpecially, being of your owne making, then to run into further miſchiefe by the wicked humour of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience? But to the purpoſe: ſay this, (to quit you with another propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition) put the caſe, that I being (as you ſee) a proper man, and in the way of good ſpeed with a handſome woman, and ſhee in ſtate able to doe for an honeſt man that would loue her, and make much of her, and I hauing intent to deale honeſtly with her; and ſhe giues me her faith and troth, and ſweares by her very ſoule that I haue her heart ſo faſt, that no man ſhall haue her hand from me: and I thinking that becauſe ſhee is old, ſhe is honeſt: and becauſe ſhe ſweares, that ſhée ſaies true, goe about my buſineſſe as ſhe bids me for ſome few dayes, and then to returne to the ioyuing vp of the matter betwixt vs; and in the meane time, after that
<pb facs="tcp:16671:6"/>I haue ſpent perhaps more then my halfe yeares wages vpon her in wine and ſugar and good cheare, and hope to come to be mercy, come and find her married to a filthy c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſoning Knaue, who by a little more money then I had in my purſe for the preſent; to bribe another raſcall like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who was the maker of the match, dwells in my hoped houſe, giues me the bagge for my money, and hath my fat old ſow in ſuch a ſnare, that there is no getting of her out againe: when I am thus handled for my good will, with this wicked old peece of whit-leather, to put my truſt in an old hogs-ſtie for my habitation, and to bee thruſt out of doores for my labour; Shall I not <hi>be Angry?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
               <p>Oh no, in any caſe: for women haue wits beyond mens rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: eſpecially, when they are paſt a child, or child-bearing, more then they that are paſt children. Oh, I tell you, it is a perilous thing to ſlippe occaſion in matters of Loue: and age is either froward or fraile, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſhould rather haue fed her humour ful ere you had left her, then to thinke that ſhe would bee vnprouided till you ſhould come againe to her: And therefore I ſay, as you ſay; <hi>I pray you be not Angrie.</hi> For I will tell you; Say that I béeing a man euery way to content an honeſt woman, and hauing vnhappily beſtowed my ſelfe vpon a woman of the worſt kind, which before I married her, being neither widow, maide nor wife, but a plaine whore: and this miſery of my daies, being by my follie brought to ſome better ſtate then ſhe was worthy: and ſéeing her ſelfe in a glaſſe growne fat through good fare and eaſe, &amp; ſetting her countenance euen with the pride of her folly, beginning to thinke better of her ſelfe then halfe the pariſh beſides, ſhould chance vpon a little kindneſſe, grow in loue with my kinſman, or he with her, and ſo they grow ſo great, that I ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd like <hi>Iohn hold my ſtaffe,</hi> while they take their pleaſure: ſhe ſhould ſit at the vpper end of the Table, and I at the neither end: ſhe lie in one Chamber, and I in another, and yet muſt not finde fault with it for feare of a ſtab, or a figge, or ſome other villanie, but with a ſaming countenance beare all, as if pudding were the onely meate of the world, while one makes hornes at mee, another moes at mee, another calls mee cuckold, another wittall; and I know all to bee true, and cannot, or dare not doe withall: Doe you thinke that fleſh and blood can beare this, and not <hi>be angry?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fern.</speaker>
               <p>Yes very well, for, as you haue fleſh and blood, ſo you haue wit and reaſon: and when your wit and reaſon can conſider, how her trade brings more commoditie, and with leſſe trauell then your traſſique: if you be not ſo wilfull that you will heare no body ſpeake but your ſelfe;
<pb facs="tcp:16671:6"/>or ſo ſcornefull, that you can endure no companion in kindneſſe: or ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous, that you will not ſpare a penny towards the nurſing of your neighbours child: or ſo proud, that you ſcorne the gift of a friend: you wil finde that ſuch a wiſe is worth too Milch cowes: and whatſoeuer the world ſaies, you are beholding to none but her: and where others begger their huſbands, ſhe hath made you the head man of the Pariſh: and then, cannot you winck at a litle fault that is ſo full of profit? Yes I warrant you and therefore I may well ſay, <hi>I pray you be not angry?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
               <p>True, it may be that ſome good aſſe that knowes not how to liue without the baſeſt trade of beggerie, will put on any <hi>Patience</hi> for profit: but from ſuch a raſcall nature God deliuer me But to requite you with as good as you bring, let me tell you: If I ſhould ſerue a man of great wealth, and hee haue a wenching humour, and hee kéeping more Maide-ſeruants in his houſe then euer meant to be true Virgins, &amp; one of theſe wilde cattle, that for the price of a red Petticote would venture the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of her placket, ſhould by a miſchance of her Maſters making, fall into a two héeld Tinpany, which could by no meanes be cured, without my conſenting to a wicked marriage for a little money; which I, by the villanie of the Trull, which would put the tricke vpon mee muſt ſéeme willingly to yéeld vnto, for feare of I know not what, to fall out I know not why: and ſo giuing a countenance of contentment; to the confuſion of my hearts comfort, when ſhee could be deliuered of this miſchiefe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that ſhee would meddle no more with any ſuch matters, begin to make a little more of her then ſhee was worthy: and ſhe thereupon ſo lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, that thee cared not for the Pariſh ſo long as the Conſtable was her friend, giue entertainment to whom ſhee luſt, and vſe me as ſhee liſt; ſet more hornes then haires on my head; and care not if I were hanged for my good will: This raſcal roundabout, without good complexion or good condition; as ill fauoured as mannered, and ſo ſpoken as wicked: béeing thus voide of grace, careleſſe of all credit, and irremoueable in her reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution for the wicked courſe of her life; this (I ſay) helliſh peece of fleſh to dominere ouer me, and with the countenance of her maſter, to make a ſlaue of her good-man, who ſhould be ſent of errands, while ſhe were with her arrants: I ſhould fetch wine for their drinking, turn the ſpit to their roaſt-meate, or walke their horſes, while they were ſadling my Fillie: and yet all this (and I ſay not what elſe) I muſt beare, as though it were no burthen for a ſmall reckoning at the weekes end for waſhing a fouls ſhirt, or ſetting of my ruffes right, or ſeething of a calues head, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſauce to a tame gooſe, or for a nod of my Maſter, that makes a nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb facs="tcp:16671:7"/>of his ſeruant: for ſuch and ſuch like matters, to put vp all matters, and ſwallow griefe ſo in my throat, that it is ready to choake me in the going downe: Is it poſſible to doe all this, that you could be, I, and not <hi>be Angrie?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fern.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, very well: for profit is ſo pleaſing, that it puts out a great many ill thoughts that would trouble a man that hath no wit; and for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, it is a good thing I muſt confeſſe: But if a man be not borne rich, and keepes himſelfe ſo, hee ſhall gaine little by ſimplifitie: and therefore as I ſaid, where <hi>patience</hi> brings pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, I ſay ſtill, beare with your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and <hi>be not Angry.</hi> But leauing to talke more of female diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentments, let mee ſay this: That I being a man of ſufficiencie to ſupply the Office of a good place, borne of a Noble houſe bred vp in all courſes requiſite for a Gentleman, haue trauelled diuers countries, ſéene much of the world by ſea and land: and through want of my fathers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, not left ſo good a portion as may maintaine my reputation, without ſome better matter then mine owne eſtate, and driuen for my better comfort, to put my fortune vnder the fauour of him, whom I know not what hath made rich: and being onely wiſe in the world, hath no féeling of Gods grace, but by a thouſand ill practiſes, findes the meane before his death to look ouer a great deal of more ground then his graue: and this Captaine of the damned crue, who is haled to hell with a world of chaines; the ſon of a begger, &amp; brother to a villaine, to gouerne ouer tho honeſty of my heart with the commandement of euill ſeruice: or finding me not for his humour, to frowne on me like an old frying-panne: or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate me like a dogge, becauſe I will not bee a Deuill: to bee employed in more vileneſſe then halfe a Chriſtian could endure to heare of: now I ſay, to ſpend my time in this miſery onely for picking of a ſallad, waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at a trencher, looking on a faire houſe, making curteſie to an old re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, hold the baſon to the rhewme, or hearing the inuſique of a rotten Cough: and after many yéeres patience in this purgatory, where all the wiſedome I haue learned, were but to corrupt the nature of a good wit, either for a trifle to be frowned at, &amp; by tricks to be wrought out: or with a liuery without a badge, to ſeeke my fortune in ſome better ſoile, to haue ſerued long for nothing, or for worſe then nothing, when diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments muſt be cancelled, and I for feare of a miſchiefe, muſt ſpeake all honour of diſhonour, and with a merry goe ſorrie, ſigh out my dayes that are no better bleſſed: when I ſhall ſee a foole graced, and better wits put downe: honeſtie ſcorned, and knauery in more account then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneable: and I conſening my ſelfe with an imagination that ſeruice
<pb facs="tcp:16671:7"/>was an heritage, where I found nothing but loſſe of time &amp; repentance; Haue I not cauſe, thinke you, with all this, <hi>to be Angry?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
               <p>And yet I ſay; <hi>I pray you be not Angry:</hi> For, if you had ſo much of the grace of God, as to make you rather leaue the hope of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then yeeld to an ill imployment, no doubt but either your priuate life will finde ſome ſecret contentment, or your patience will finde ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where aduancement of your vertues: and therefore rather be ioyfull of Gods bleſſing, then impatient with your fortune; and thinke not amiſſe that I ſay, <hi>I pray you be not Angry.</hi> But to requite you; Say that I hauing more money in my purſe then a wiſe man would part with, but vpon the better reckoning, ſhould be perſwaded to play the vſurer, and ſo with little reward to make my money multiply, &amp; by the cunning wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of a cunny catching Knaue. I ſhould be brought (in hope of gaine) to take in pawne for my mony, ſome leaſe of a good farme, or péece of rich plate: which being not fetche by the day of payment, would returne mee more then double my money: put my money out of my hands, which I haue fared full hard to get together, and I at the day glad of my forfeit, hoping to gaine more then a good conſcience would away withall, finde my leaſe not worth a point, by a former deede of gift, or ſuch a conuei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance as carrieth all away from my fingers, and leaue me (for all my cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Law,) to pleade repentance to my folly: or my plate challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for ſome peece of pilferie, and I brought to trouble for I know not what, and to get out I know not how, till I haue brought my ſtocke to a poore ſtate, where I may ſée the iuſt reward of vſury, when I looke in my purſe, and find nothing, Would not this make one <hi>Angry?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fern.</speaker>
               <p>Not a whit: for knaues will bee knaues, and fooles muſt bee bitten ere they will be wiſe: of which if you be none, no doubt but there are enough in the world. And ſince all the <hi>Anger</hi> in the world will not recouer a penny loſſe, let me ſay to you, as you ſay to me; <hi>I pray be not Angry.</hi> And let me tell you, that vpon a time it was my hap to haue a friend (as I thought) whom I loued dearely; and building vpon the care of his conſcience, that for a world of wealth he would not play the Iew with mee: it fell out that I hauing more then a moneths minde to a wench aboue a yeare old, whoſe worthineſſe euery way might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a farre better ſeruant then my ſelfe; and yet it had ſo fallen out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt vs, that our affections were ſo ſetled, that I thought (without death) there could be no remoue: and therefore fearing no fortune, rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much vpon her loue, louing (as I ſaid) my imagined friend more then a wiſe man ſhould do (for there is a meaſure to be kept in all things)
<pb facs="tcp:16671:8"/>made him acquainted with my ſecrecie, touching the intent to ſteale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my Miſtris from the place where ſhe had no pleaſure to be kept in, as ſhe had béene long like a chicken in a coope: and to the performing of this purpoſe, hoping to haue vſe of his beſt helpe, deliuer him a ring, or a iewell of ſome value, to preſent vnto my loue, when I know his meanes better then mine owne, to haue acceſſe vnto her without ſuſpition: and he after a world of proteſtations ſealed with too many oathes, to deale ſo faithfully, carefully, and ſecretly for me as my heart could deſire, when faith there was none, nor care of me, nor ſecrecy, but in kéeping all from me, when like a diſſembling Iew, be vſeth my iewell for a meane to rob me of my better iewell: when he preſented it as from himſelfe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealing ſome matter of ſecrecie betwixt vs, vnpleaſing to her, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to my profit, with inchanting tearmes winnes her affection, and borroweth my money to cut my throate, till hauing carried away my miſtris, he either laugh at me, or write me a letter of excuſe to collogue with mee: When I thinke how with truſting a Knaue, I haue played the foole, in conſcience ſay, if euer man would fall out with himſelfe, haue not I cauſe <hi>to be angry?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
               <p>No: for as you ſaid to me, Knaues will be Knaues; and in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of loue, he that will not be the follower of his owne cauſe, may hap to bee ouerthrowne in his owne ſuite: and to looke for conſtancy in a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, eſpecially of yong yeares, when bribes and gifts are able to worke great matters in thoſe courſes, it is a meere folly: for, ſay that ſome are (I know not how many) as conſtant as <hi>Penelope,</hi> yet let <hi>Danac</hi> take heede of a golden ſhower in her lap: and therefore, <hi>I pray you be not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry.</hi> For let me tell you, to be deceiued by a friend, it is an ordinary matter; to looſe a wench, it is a thouſand mens fortune: and therefore ſince ſhe was ſo fickle to truſt to, think her better loſt then found: and for him, get your golden iewels &amp; your money from him, and let him walke with his wicked houſehold-ſtuffe: and let me tell you of a diſcontentment of minde. It was my hap (I may ſay my ill hap) to caſt my affection of late vpon a very proper young man, of a pure complection, neither effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate, nor courſe faced, neither of letherſellers, nor painters company, but a good feature and well coloured: and for his countenance, neither Paules-ſteeple height, nor with the fall of the tide; but carried in ſo good a meaſure, as ſhewed his wits no more out of order then his members: for his hoyce, neither Treble nor Baſe, but a good meane: and his ſpeech neither Rhetoricall, nor Logicall, nor Tragicall, nor Colaſticall; but ſuch, as neither too litle, nor too much, anſwering directly to euery queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<pb facs="tcp:16671:8"/>and ſpeaking neceſſarily vpon good occaſſion, wan him ſuch commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for his diſcretion, as increaſing much my affection, made mee (as I thought) vpon good iudgement, make him a great ſubiect of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment: in briefe, I ſingled him out of company, to make him my companion, tooke him into my houſe, beſtowed bountifully vpon him, let him not want any thing that was néedfull for him: my table to dine at, a faire chamber for his lodging, yea &amp; ſometime made him my bedfellow, furniſhed him with money, horſe, apparell, bookes, and credit for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he would demaund: yea, and in mine abſence truſted him with the gouernment of my whole houſe; till my fauour b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed in his folly that, at the firſt I ſaw not, ſuch a preſumption of his owne worthineſſe, as I liked not, when controulling euen my ſelfe for a trifle, himſelfe to blame in the ſelfe ſame nature for a greater matter, thinking all too little that was done for him, and vrging more then was méete for him: at laſt not able to ſuppreſſe the veneme of his pride, till his hart made his head ſwell as bigge as a cods-head; in recompence of all my kindneſſe, playe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> falſe with my ſeruant maide, ſteales away my eldeſt daughter, robs my cofers, troubles my conſcience, crackes my credit, befooles my wit, and doth what hee may to ſeeke the ruine of my ſtate; Is it poſſible that a man could thinke of ſuch a villaine, and not <hi>be Angrie?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fern.</speaker>
               <p>Yea very well; and I ſay vnto you: <hi>I pray you be not Angry:</hi> For, ſtill Knaues will be Knaues; and a man had neede eate a buſhell of ſalt with a man, before he grow too farre to truſt him: for hee was a worlding, and out of the ſimplicitie of your honeſty, thinking him to be bee that he was not, might learne him to truſt his like, or any at all, at leaſt with your houſe, your daughter, (if you haue any) or your ſeruants, if you keepe any: and hauing <hi>patience</hi> with your lacke of iudgement, doe for your daughter, as you haue cauſe in nature and reaſon, and pray in charitie for his ſoule, what euer become of his carkaſſe: and ſince (I hope) you will take this for no ill councell, I ſay as I did, <hi>I pray you be not Angrie.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
